good morning to all of you
welcome to legal matters by Sai Baba
Sankara
in this video
we are going to discuss a Supreme Court
decision
regarding the multiplier Theory
you all know that the multiplayer Theory
will be applied on the death of a person
so the age
is expected to be alive suppose in case
he is alive then the emoluments he takes
all these things will be taken to
consideration and the motor vehicles
crimes tribunal they will award the
compensation by using the multiplayer
Theory
but what happens in case of Bachelors
this is more important while dealing
with the case of via serum
and another versus ICICI Lombard General
Insurance Company Limited and others in
similar pin number seven zero double
five by 2022
dated 29th September 2022 two Judges
Bench honorable Justice says
they clearly held that age of the
deceased Bachelor and not age of the
dependents has to be taken as the basis
for the multiplier Theory right it is
very clearly stated
now we'll go to the facts of the case so
actually this is a case for a claim of
compensation for a person for a bachelor
who is involved in a motorcycle accident
right so in
2017 uh 2017 or so
that this is the bachelor was going on a
motorcycle and he was hit by
the opposite coming back
he received a fatal injuries no doubt uh
he is the son of the so-called planet
that is a gyasiram
and actually she got him admitted in a
hospital but actually due to the Fatal
injuries he succumbed to dangerous he
has succumbed on the account of the okay
on account of the accident he died so
they claimed the motor car vehicle
compensation as the mother is the
dependent on The Bachelor son
now the tribunal calculated the
percentage of the multiplier at 18
percent because suppose if the decision
person who is aged about 21 years at the
particular point of time his lifespan is
around eight years so actually they
stated that he was earning actually he
was earning about 10 000 or so but it
was calculated 3063 to 3683 attainment
compensation of certain amount was
awarded by the Tribunal
right here the point is the I say is a
lumbar company they have not said they
are not satisfied therefore they went in
appeal to the high court
the high court yes has reduced the
multiplier by nine because
they have calculated the age of this
particular woman she is raised about 40
years or so so she will die at the age
of 80 or 90. so therefore they have
reduced the multiplier to nine once
again this woman not is satisfied with
the high court judgment she approaches
the final Authority that the top coat or
Supreme Court of India now the matter
has come before the two judges page
ravindra Bhatt and Sudan
right now please remember
honorable Supreme Court
based on or held that the age of the
diseased it has to be taken into account
because on Whose uh on whose behalf we
are doing given the compensation only
for the deceased person on his behalf
the dependent will take but you should
not take the age of the dependent into
consideration
so please remember the age of the
bachelor is to be taken into
consideration therefore the tribunal MD
climb seminal that the original
entrepreneur which fixes the multiplier
that is 18 is 100 correct because no
doubt she was working with some now this
woman as she is working with some
informal sector and now her pay is fixed
around
4107 is including excluding the cutoff
cell and all the things that they have
clearly stated that multiplayer of 18
should be added so 40 percent of the
conversation should be restored back to
her this is the very good judgment on
behalf of it will be useful for all
persons who are involved in the accident
cases here an important point you have
to know I will tell in Telugu also
important point out no is the age of the
diseased has to be calculated for the
multiplayer Theory not the age of the
dependent dependent foreign
thank you